University of Connecticut,
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Handicapped Homemaker Project Records.
undated, 1954-1972.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
University of Connecticut. Handicapped Homemaker Project.
5 linear feet.
MSS19800005
The project lasted five years and was officially titled “Work Simplification in the Area of Child Care for Physically Handicapped Women”. The main work of the project took place between 1955 and 1960.
History
This five-year project, officially titled “Work Simplification in the Area of Child Care for Physically Handicapped Women”, was sponsored by the School of Home Economics, University of Connecticut, in cooperation with the “Team Approach” Committee on Research Demonstrations and Workshops Concerning Physically Handicapped Women. The main work of the project occurred between 1955 and 1960. Among the goals of the project were (1) to demonstrate the ways in which the competence of physically handicapped mothers of pre-school children may be increased in the area of child care, through the application of the principles of work simplification, (2) to explore the vocational rehabilitation possibilities of physically handicapped women, in the area of child care, for work in nursery schools, in day care centers or as “baby sitters”, and (3) to study the effectiveness of the methods developed in terms of human values and family relationships as well as in increased efficiency. The project coordinators and participants prepared booklets and bibliographies on various aspects of the research, conducted workshops, and prepared photographic exhibits illustrating how the project's recommendations helped the handicapped homemaker in performing her daily work.
Scope and Content
The collection contains reports, publications, bibliographies, articles, pamphlets, proceedings, memoranda, correspondence, and photographs pertaining to the project.
Arrangement
Series I: Administrative Records (undated, 1954-1972), is arranged in seven subseries. Project Reports contains the project proposal and annual reports of the committee. In-house Publications consists of books published and bibliographies compiled by the School of Home Economics, University of Connecticut, pertaining to the project. Related Publications includes published articles and books that contain information about the project or were used as reference material. The Audio-Visual Materials subseries contains pamphlets and notes describing films, slides and exhibits on the rehabilitation of handicapped homemakers. Workshops consists of the proceedings of various workshops conducted or attended by project coordinators. Correspondence includes incoming correspondence, outgoing memos, and a list of overseas contacts. Handicapped Children contains materials relating to a subsequent project on clothing for handicapped children.
Series II: Photographs (undated, 1956-1959), consists of photographs taken to illustrate various aspects of the project. These photographs are stored both in albums (arranged by person) for regular-size illustrations, and in flat boxes for oversized materials used in exhibits.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of records pertaining to activities, events, programs and individuals associated with the institution. See especially: Elizabeth E. May Papers. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Handicapped—Clothing.; Handicapped parents—United States.; Handicapped parents—Connecticut.; Child care—United States.; Connecticut—Education—Universities and colleges.; Storrs (Conn.)—Education—Universities and colleges.; Connecticut—Social issues—Handicapped.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Bibliographies.; Albums.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Project Records were transferred to Historical Manuscripts and Archives in 1980 by Elizabeth Eckhardt May, Dean of the School of Home Economics.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Administrative Records, undated, 1954-1960
  - Project Reports
    - Project proposal, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Research project suggestions, 1954-1955 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Progress report to Home Economics faculty, 1956 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Meeting agenda, 1956 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Progress reports, 1955-1959 (Box 1:, Folder 5-8)
    - Final report, 1955-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 9-10)
  - In-house Publications
    - “Child Care Equipment for Physically Handicapped Mothers”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - “Suggestions for Physically Handicapped Mothers on Clothing For Preschool Children”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - “Where There's A Will...”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - “Work Simplification in Child Care: Teaching Materials for the Rehabilitation of Handicapped Homemakers”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - “You Can Do Family Laundry... With Hand Limitations”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - “A Selected Bibliography on the Rehabilitation of Handicapped Homemakers”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - “Bibliography on Home Management”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - “Bibliography on Work Simplification in Food Preparation for Handicapped Homemakers”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - “Homemaker Rehabilitation: A Selected Bibliography for the Layman, and for Professional Staff in Health and Welfare”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - “Play Experiences Handicapped Mothers May Share With Young Children”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - “Suggestions for Physically Handicapped Mothers on Clothing for Preschool Children” (Bibliography), undated (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - “The Rehabilitation of Handicapped Homemakers: A Selected Bibliography”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Related Publications
    - Elizabeth Eckhardt May, Neva R. Waggoner, and Eleanor M. Boettke, Homemaking for the Handicapped, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - “Handicapped Mothers”, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - “Homemaking Instruction for Handicapped Children” by Elizabeth Eckhardt May, 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - “Lillian Moeller Gilbreth, 1878-1972: Pioneer in the Rehabilitation of the Handicapped Homemaker” by Elizabeth Eckhardt May (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - “New Function for Clothing—Help for the Handicapped”, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - “One Armed Mother”, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - “Suggestions Concerning the Vocational Rehabilitation of Orthopedically Handicapped Homemakers”, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 29-30)
    - “Suggestions for the Rehabilitation of the Physically Handicapped Homemaker”, by Elizabeth Eckhardt May, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - “UConn Study Helps in Home”, by Whitney Jacobs, undated (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - “Vocational Rehabilitation for Handicapped Homemakers”, by Elizabeth Eckhardt May, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - “The Child Amputee and His Parents”, by Ellen Buttrup and Elizabeth Eckhardt May, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
    - “Who Should Rehabilitate the Handicapped Homemaker?”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 35)
    - “Work Simplification for Handicapped Mothers”, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Audio-Visual Materials
    - “Rehabilitation of Handicapped Homemakers: Films, Publications, Exhibits”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 37)
    - “Rehabilitation of Handicapped Homemakers: Motion Pictures, Slides, Bulletins”, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
    - Notes on Exhibit of Self-help Clothing for Pre-schoolers, undated (Box 1:, Folder 39)
    - Film analyses, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
    - Film descriptions, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - Workshops
    - Handicapped Homemakers, 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - Program for workshop on “The Team Approach for the Of the Handicapped Homemaker”, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
    - The Team Approach to the Rehabilitation of the Handicapped Homemaker, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Program, The Rehabilitation of the Handicapped Homemaker, 1957 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Proceedings, Work Simplification for Disabled and for Normal Homemakers, 1957 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
    - Help for Handicapped Women, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
    - Proceedings, Conference on Rehabilitation and Work Simplification, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 48)
    - Proceedings, AHEA Pre-Convention Workshop Expanding the Services of the Home Economist in Rehabilitation, 1960 (Box 1:, Folder 49)
    - Report of the Proceedings, ISRD Conferences, The Physically Disabled and their Environment, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 50)
    - Proceedings, Rehabilitation of the Physically Handicapped in Homemaking Activities, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence
    - General Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 52)
    - Memos to the Connecticut Team Approach Committee on Research, Demonstrations and Workshops concerning Physically Handicapped Homemakers, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 53)
  - Handicapped Children
    - Final Report, “A Collaborative Study on the Selection and Some Adaptation of Clothing for Children with Physical Handicaps”, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
    - Survey for Parents of Physically handicapped children, undated (Box 1:, Folder 55)
    - Article, “Clothing for Children with Physical Handicaps,” By Eleanor M. Boettke, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 56)
    - Clari Bare, Eleanor Boettke, and Neva Waggoner, Self-Help Clothing for Handicapped Children, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 57)
- Series II: Photographs, undated, 1956-1959
  - Handicapped Homemaker Research Project, No. 37, Office of Vocational Rehabilitation and University of Connecticut, 1956-1957 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - Master Files of Photographs, 1956-1959 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
  - Master Files of Photographs, 1956-1959 (Box 3:, Folder 60)
  - Photographs and labels - exhibit, undated (Box 3:, Folder 61)
  - Unidentified photograph of dressing child, undated (Box 3:, Folder 62)
  - Photographs of kitchen utensils Script notes for slide series, undated (Box 3:, Folder 63)
  - “Baby Bathing with Hand Limitations—Simplified”, undated (Box 3:, Folder 64)
  - “A Wheelchair Mother Prepares Formula”, undated (Box 3:, Folder 65)
  - “You Can Do Family Laundry with Hand Limitations”, undated (Box 3:, Folder 66)
  - Photographs for exhibits (oversize), 1956-1959 (Box 4:, Folder 67)
  - Photographs for exhibits (oversize), 1956-1959 (Box 5:, Folder 68)
  - Slides for slide series, “A Wheelchair Mother Prepares Formula”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 69)
  - Slides for slide series, “You Can Do Family Laundry with Hand Limitations”, undated (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - Photographs for exhibits (oversize), 1956-1959 (Box 6:, Folder 71)
  - Posters, undated (Box 6:, Folder 72)